[Music]
Hey. Hey. Hey.
Heat. Heat.
[Music]
Hello, good evening everybody. Good
evening, good day wherever you are in
the world, whether it's day or night.
Welcome to episode 264
of the Ask a Bidget Show. I hope
everybody is doing great. Today we have
no super chats. Everybody, I hope you
all asked good questions. Please do. But
before we get into the questions, let's
see who all is there on the live chat. I
can see Britishes. I can see Sharma. Uh
Dave Dave from Yeah. Dave, Ritik, Pawar,
Satish, Dave, Yashika, Jet, Malani,
Geopolitical Dub, our good friend from
Indor, Zeba, Badada, Unknown, GK,
Anonymous Scientist, Boswar, Vehav,
Kanadia, Swami, Jan, Yashwan, Sudir,
Niha, Sharma, Rashmi, Ratour from
Rajasthan, hello Martian from Mars.
Hello. Flick edits. Avin Dirj Kamat says
good morning. Well, good morning to you.
Chira Gavasti says good evening. Well,
thank you. Good evening. Geost strategy
was amazing. Well, I'm glad you liked
it. Sedat Adika likes the geopolitics
series. I'm glad you do. Suash Reddi
Haran Gokul Big Smoka. Praal from
Kolkata. Aayush Singh, Pratam Sharma,
Rohan, Hitanua,
Barat First, Duv Durya, Tanmay Pande,
Hayatim
Roy, freedom from outcome from Canada.
Kiraasti,
anonymous scientist again. Nabanita Das,
Dungar Singh, Johan is excited for World
War II. Well, I'm not, sir. I'm not. Um,
Udai Kiran
Commando is here. Martian is concerned
about my my health. My health is
fantastic. Well, thank you for asking.
Anyway, Lone Walker and so many other
people. Okay, let's take some questions.
Let's take some questions. Let's begin
with our friend Panoi. Prrenai from
Kolkata. Okay, what's the question? The
US has bombed Iran's nuclear facilities
and yet Iran hasn't retaliated. What
does this silence indicate? Is regime
change now inevitable or is Iran playing
a longer game? Well, if you did watch my
geost strategy episode 8, I I have
estimated that the probability of regime
change in Thran is
6%
over the next 6 months. So, it's a
pretty low probability
um because of variety of factors. Watch
the episode, you will know. Um so, yeah,
Iran, the US has bombed Iran's nuclear
facilities. Iran hasn't retaliated. Why
is it so? Why is Iran not retaliating?
First of all, there's a tremendous
geographical distance between Iran and
the US. How do you retaliate against the
US when it's thousands, tens of
thousands of kilometers away, 10,000
plus kilometers away? How do you do
that? Does Iran have the means to
retaliate that far? And if it does,
doesn't it invite even more and even
harer uh responses from the US? Right.
So, Iran is being, I think, pragmatic.
they understand that you can't mess with
the US. The US is way too powerful.
Um, so that's one reason. Secondly, it
could also indicate that the Iran
Iranian nuclear facilities aren't
destroyed. We have seen satellite
evidence that the Iranians were removing
materials and possibly something some
other stuff, maybe equipment, etc. from
the facilities a couple of days before
they were bombed because Mr. Trump has
been signaling this for the past two
weeks that you know your nuclear
facilities could be bombed. He's been
signaling this very publicly, maybe
maybe deliberately to give Iran an
indication of what they should do. So
maybe Mr. Trump doesn't want to destroy
the Iranian nuclear program entirely.
Yeah, maybe. So there's so much so many
factors in this. So in my opinion,
regime change is not inevitable. I think
the possibility of regime change is
remote
because it takes a lot to do regime
change.
The only way to reliably carry a carry
out regime change is either if you have
lots of assets within the country who
will
carry out regime change for you which
means you know mass protests and
violence and whatnot which the Americans
can't do or you puts on the ground which
is super expensive and it it's it's very
complicated and you need a full-scale
invasion bigger than the invasion of
Iraq in 2003. So that's why it's very
difficult to see this happening.
Uh okay.
Arun says Qatar has closed its airspace
and the UAE is also considering closing
its airspace. So are we are we heading
into a regional war? Let's take a look
at the map.
Let's take a look at the map.
So we are talking about the Gulf region
which is right essentially in our
neighborhood next door. Um so okay I
haven't seen this news. This is news
that you're reporting which I'm hearing
for the first time. Uh Qatar has closed
its airspace while Qatar is right here.
It's right essentially in the in the
Persian Gulf, right? Not the Arabian
Gulf. It's the Persian Gulf by the way.
Uh so the the the war is heating up,
right? And because the US has gotten
involved in this matter,
it is a nonzero probability that Iran
may strike at US assets in the region in
the wider region. The US has struck at
Iran directly using B2 uh stealth
bombers. So Iran may may choose to
retaliate against the United States in
the region and the US has multiple air
bases and military bases and naval bases
and whatnot in the region in the entire
West Asia region across the region and
many of these are hosted by nations in
this region and which is why it makes
sense you know for temp for these
nations as a precautionary measure to at
least temporarily close their airspace.
So maybe that is the reason why they're
doing it. And yeah, the possibility the
the possibility is that we may be
heading towards a regional war if Iran
chooses to respond in some way.
Rohan says, "Which country has the best
nuclear submarine technology? France,
Russia, or the US? Is the French and
Russian nuclear subs are open to buy for
India? Which one should we get and in
what quantity?" Thank you. Okay. Which
country is the best nuclear submarine
capability? I think it would technology.
I think it would be the US and then it
would it would be Russia in my opinion.
The Chinese also have nuclear subs. We
also have nuclear subs. The French also
have nuclear submarines. The French
would have pretty good nuclear
submarines, I'm sure. And uh overall the
Japanese don't have nuclear submarines,
but their submarines that their
conventional submarines are outstanding.
Even their decommissioned submarines are
better than most nations, you know,
operational submarines. That's how good
the Japanese submarines are. The Shyu
class submarine and so on. Uh the UK
also has nuclear subs if I'm not
mistaken. I suppose they do. Yeah. Um so
it's not like we have a market in which
we can go shopping and okay, I'll take
one of this and two of that and one of
this. That's not how it is. You you most
nations won't offer you nuclear
submarine technology or or or nuclear
submarines to for for purchase. The
Americans are now revisiting their AUK
US submarine deal in which Australia was
supposed to get a bunch of nuclear
submarines from the US. Now it is being
revisited revisited and reconsidered by
the US. Yeah.
Um India has in the past acquired a
variety of not a variety of but like two
or three nuclear nuclear submarines from
the from the Russians. ALA class
submarines which we have generally
called INS Chakra. INS Chakra the first,
the second and so on.
Um, so these have always been given to
India on lease, long lease like 10-year
leases and all that. Um, I'm not sure if
the French have opened have have offered
India uh nuclear submarines to purchase.
I'm not sure if they have. Uh, my what's
my view on this? My view is that India
should develop its own nuclear submarine
technology iteratively. You build one
boat, test it out, see how it performs,
learn the lessons. Obviously, there's
going to be drawbacks any time. Learn
the lessons. Then build a new one which
is better which which incorporates the
lessons you learned. Then you test that.
Then you find some shortcomings, some
drawbacks, some positives and so on so
forth. Then you build one more boat and
incorporate the learnings in that. And
over time, over the years, over the
decades, you you end up with very very
sophisticated nuclearpowered submarines.
So we are we are in the process of doing
that. So what we should do? We should
have a parallel thing. We should develop
our own submarines, nuclear submarines
with miniaturaturized nuclear reactors
and so on. And at the same time, we can
also keep on leasing Russian submarines
and cooperating with the Russians.
That's what we should do. We should
always be open to other offers. But
other offers, we have to evaluate them
very closely because other nations with
other nations we don't have the kind of
relationship that we have with the
Russians. So,
so yeah, that's the deal.
Okay,
now let's see some other questions. Uh,
geopolitical dubet says, uh, the US has
nukes in Turkey, even in Pakistan, but
do they have nuclear weapons in Japan or
South Korea? If not, why why aren't they
in US nuclear umbrella? Because they are
not NATO members.
Um, okay. So, we know that the US has
nuclear weapons deployed in Turkey. also
in the Netherlands, also in Germany if
I'm not mistaken and some other
countries
uh and Pakistan most likely hosts US
nuclear weapons. Most likely those nukes
are not Pakistani nukes. They are US
nukes most likely. So that is aimed at
us. Those are American nuclear weapons
aimed at us from from our territory, our
temporarily lost territory. The question
is do the Americans have nukes in Japan
and South Korea? As far as I know, I'm
not sure. As far as I know, it's like
there's a denial that the US has nukes
in Japan. I think in the past, South
Korea used to host nuclear weapons from
the US if I'm not mistaken. Let's
quickly fact check that. Did South Korea
in the past host US nuclear weapons? Did
South
Korea host US nuclear
weapons in the past?
The US first deployed deployed nukes in
South Korea 58. Numbers peaked in the
late 1960s.
And what about now? Withdrawal. The US
withdrew nukes from South Korea in 1991
and so on. But the US continues to
guarantee South Korea's nuclear security
under its nuclear umbrella. And the
same, I suppose, applies to Japan. Let's
let's also fact check Japan. As far as I
know, the US has never deployed nukes
there. They've tested nukes there
and Japan is very sensitive to U to
nuclear weapons. That's why Oh, it
appears they did.
The US did store nuclear weapons on
Japan in the past in Okinawa. Okay. So,
when they held Okinawa, they had
deployed nukes there, but then it was
returned to Japanese control in 1972.
Um and yeah, of course, Japan also has
the protection of the alleged US nuclear
umbrella. So both Japan and South Korea
come under the protection of the US
nuclear umbrella. I imagine Australia
also does potentially New Zealand also.
We have to look into it, you know, case
by case. Uh so they these nations do
have the benefit of the US nuclear
umbrella and South Korea did have US
nuclear weapons. Apparently, even Japan
did as long as Okinawa was completely
controlled by the US.
Okay. Um, Ichino senpai
senpai says, "Could you, okay, let's not
speak in a Japanese accent. Could you
please explain the part of your AI
podcast with Omakan Sony where he said
that the value of money will diminish in
the future?" Well, that's one quote from
a two and a half hour podcast that I
don't remember right now. So,
uh, what was the context? It was a long
podcast. we discussed so many things
uh the value of look I don't I don't
recall off the top of of my head right
now okay uh so I'll have to look into it
and maybe I can get back to you if you
can ask me during the next live stream
the same question tomorrow for day after
tomorrow for example which will again be
a non-super chat liveream I'm telling
you right now itself okay so you can ask
me the same question that day Wednesday
day after tomorrow and if I can catch a
question I will answer it but right now
I don't remember what what the context
was so sorry.
Okay.
Uh Shira Aasti says, "Just as the US has
helped Ukraine during the war, do you
think Russia will do the same this time
with Iran or have they stretched
themselves too far?" That's a good
question. That's a great question. Let's
take a look at the map because the map
generally answers a lot of the questions
if we know how to use the map. So, let's
take a look at the map. I'll tell you.
Um
so we have two situations.
One is Ukraine, one is Iran. Uh one is
Ukraine, Russia, one is uh Israel, Iran.
So when it comes to Ukraine, you can see
that it neighbors
it it neighbors multiple NATO nations.
One of the biggest is is Poland,
obviously a very powerful nation. So it
is in the neighborhood of multiple NATO
nations.
It has common borders with multiple NATO
nations. And these NATO nations are
extensions of the US. These are vasals
of the US. And that's why it's very easy
for the US to directly provide all kinds
of support to Ukraine. Not just
financial and diplomatic support, but
also weapons, arms, ammunition, whatnot,
because of this common shared borders
that Ukraine has with other NATO
nations. Okay. So that's how it's so
easy for the US because they have
completely vasalized Western Europe.
That's why it's very easy for the US to
uh supply Ukraine with various kinds of
uh help. Now when it comes to Iran,
okay,
if Russia wants to help Iran in some
way, how can they do it? Does Russia
have any any vasals in the region? Well,
you could say that you know the central
Asian nations are kind of in the Russian
sphere of influence but not entirely
vasals. But then there is the Caspian
Sea, the sea of Kashup allegedly the
Caspian Sea. And if you look at the
Caspian Sea, you can see there is a
significant Russian uh
coastline over there. So if you if you
look here, you have this is Russian
territory over here. for example,
Russia, the the Republic of Dagistan
within Russia. So, this is all part of
Russia. And how far is it from Iran?
Let's just do a pretty quick
look into it very quickly. It's about
500 600 km away from Iran. So using the
Caspian Sea, Russia could resupply Iran
if they want to, if they determine that
it makes sense for them to do so. But
they don't have a common border with
Iran, but they're not very far from
Iranian territory and they can, you
know, use maritime means to uh supply
help to Iran. The question is, will
Russia choose to do do so if if push
comes to shove and that remains to be
seen. Thus far, Mr. Putin is making very
diplomatic statements that you know in
this in this war we have a lot of
Russian speaking Iranian Russian
speaking Israelis and we would not like
to get involved in this matter or
something. That's the kind of hint that
he is giving but words are okay. At the
end of the day it's actions that count
and we'll see about that.
Anonymous scientist says there's news
that India is modifying the Agni 5 to
make it a surfaceto-surface bunker
buster missile. What are my thoughts?
I'm glad we should we should modify all
missiles to do all kind of stuff. Um
what I had read briefly like today or
yesterday is that India is modifying the
AGNI AGN5 missile to to and it's
modifying the missile such that it can
carry conventional payloads. So the 5 is
a strategic missile and its purpose thus
far has been to potentially uh deliver
nuclear warheads to wherever they need
to be delivered. U but now we are
modifying it to carry conventional
warheads also if required. So
conventional explosives non- nuclear
explosives and possibly if you can make
it a surfaceto-surface it's always it's
already a surfaceto-surface missile.
Bunker buster I'm not sure. Bunker
buster bombs are a whole different
category of bombs. You don't use
something like the AGN to do that. You
generally have an overflight with a
strategic bomber and you do that. But I
don't know. So I haven't seen the bunker
bunker buster news, but I know that the
missile is being uh modified somewhat,
which should not take too long to do.
Okay. Um
Okay, let's see this. Duh je says uh how
do you see India US relations going on
they're talking about imposing 500
tariffs in Russia India China Pakistan
has become a US was from the Chinese was
the US is a bigger short-term threat now
not short-term I wouldn't say the US is
a short-term threat Pakistan is a
short-term threat long-term threats yeah
see because India is growing right as
India's economy is growing there's
nobody that can stop that from happening
unless you take very super drastic
measures. So India's economy is keep
going to keep on growing. It's projected
to keep on growing at 6% 7% plus
whatever percentage plus every year for
the foreseeable future which means that
by a 2040 horizon India will be a 105
trillion economy possibly possibly which
means India could be on on on the verge
of eventually becoming the next China.
When that happens your big adversary is
not Pakistan it's the US because the US
doesn't want new rivals to emerge. So
how do I see India US relations there in
in a tense period? Mr. Trump has
completely upended everything. He's
become super transactional. He has
become super friendly towards Pakistan
because he's personally invested in
Pakistan. Right? He seeks to extract
resources um um exploit resources like
oil and gas and rare earths. He's also
investing in the in the Pakistani um
cryptocurrency sector and so on. and he
has good friends in the Pakistani
military. Mr. Aim Moner, Mr. whoever
else, Shabbaz Sharif is also. So
Pakistan is a full-scale US patal and
Pakistan also hosts US nuclear weapons.
So yeah, there is the deal. So India US
relations are going through a tense
period, not a very friendly period.
Trump is making false claims of
immediating in the India Pakistan thing
which are completely unfounded,
completely false and he's threatening
all kinds of tariffs on India and uh and
he's being very pro Pakistan and so on.
So there's trade negotiations going on
right now between India and the US and
the US seems to be adopting maximalist
measures and making maximalist demands.
They want us to swallow their
agricultural products which we don't
want because their agriculture and dairy
products are contaminated with GMOs and
whatnot. It's what makes Americans sick
and obese and we don't want that garbage
coming to India.
But they want us to to to accept all
that. So there are fundamental issues uh
between the two nations and that is
something that needs that will need to
be resolved in some manner and obviously
we will not compromise the health of our
citizens by by importing American
farm produce and dairy products and so
on.
Okay.
Yeah. Let's see. Um
uh Janvi says, "Don't you think Britain
should be divided into into two
countries? One Christian majority and
another Islamic Britain." Well, I I
fully support this proposal. It is a
valid and just proposal. uh there is a
significant Islamic uh population in
Britain and uh I suppose they they are
not happy with with their Christian
neighbors
and they would like a different form of
government and so what whatever it is
that goes on with them. So I am fully in
support of of partitioning
the the the UK into at least two
countries so that the rights of the
Islamic citizens are are protected and
they get what they need. So I completely
agree with uh John Vij over here
totally.
Um,
Malik say is saying that why is no one
taking unmanned naval submarines
seriously?
Well, unmanned undersea vehicles or
unmanned naval submarines, whatever you
want to call them, they
they have a lot of potential, a lot of
technological challenges.
So essentially the thing is this when
you have a vehicle that operates
underwater it's very hard to control it
remotely. How do you control it
remotely? It's deep underwater. Uh
electromagnetic signals don't reach
there very easily and those can be
intercepted which is why there is
minimal communication between surface
and and submarines right because those
signals can be intercepted. Um and if
you have a vehicle without humans then
how does it take decisions make
decisions and so on. So there are all
kinds of issues not uncsurmountable
issues but significant technological uh
issues and barriers when it comes to
unmanned naval submarines but there are
many nations that are working on this
including us including India but those
things we typically don't speak about we
don't shout about this from the top of
the roof from the rooftops because this
is all sensitive technology and the
nations that lead in this will end up
leading the world in variety of ways
right so that's Okay,
says Pakistan shows unconditional
support to Iran yet it is growing ties
with the US. Pakistan also nominated
Trump for peace prize, Nobel Peace Prize
and Trump is currently bombing Iran. Can
you please explain the dynamics of the
relation? What's that to explain? It's
very simple.
If you if you have been a viewer of this
channel, you will understand that there
is a fundamental difference between
words and actions.
the difference between words and
actions. I can say whatever I want. I
can say all kinds of nice things but if
I'm a nasty person, I will then do
something else. So Pakistan is the serum
nation. They will your the the so-called
unconditional support sir that you are
mentioning. Please realize okay ve that
this unconditional support is verbal
support. talk talk talk talk talk. But
when it comes to actual support, they
are supporting Israel in the US.
Pakistan hosts US nuclear weapons on its
soil. It has given access to the US to
various air bases and whatnot. We saw in
the past few days American aircraft
flying over Pakistani territory and
monitoring Iran.
So this is all in support of Israel,
right? And Pakistan claims it doesn't
even recognize the state of Israel but
it is supporting Israel's war against
Iran. So Pakistan is that sort of
nation. It's a mercenary nation. They
claim to be the nation of Islam Pakistan
or whatever. But they are working
they're supporting Israel which a lot of
the Islamic world may possibly consider
to be an enemy of Islam. Possibly
possibly okay I'm not I'm not saying
that a lot of people are here making
such claims. So if Pakistan is one of
the great leaders of Islam, well, what
are they doing here? So that is typical
of Pakistan. They'll say one thing, do
another, they are a mercenary nation.
They're a nation for hire. They're a
nation for sale. So no surprise
over here.
Okay. Mclivven says if Ukraine, Iran and
Pakistan are hearland entry points with
Russia handling Ukraine in India
handling Pakistan, why has the RAI
abandoned Iran? Why isn't China showing
support to Iran? Let's take a look at
the map. And it's a complex question
that Mlean has asked us. Take let's take
a look at the map.
And there seem to be some assumptions
behind this, but let's let's take a look
at all of that. So according to
Mackander's
thesis,
the world island thesis and the
heartland rimland thesis, u the
heartland of the world is the Eurasian
heartland which is central Asia. It's u
much of China, Mongolia, much of
Siberia, Russia, all of that. That's the
heartland. And according to Mckender,
whoever controls the heartland will
control the world island. And uh the
rimland nations according to Mackander
are not destined to rule the world. It's
only those who control the heartland who
will rule the world eventually. And
according to Mackander,
Ukraine is the entry point to the
heartland from the west, right? Because
it's the dividing zone between Western
Europe and Russia essentially. So
according to Mackender, according to
this thesis, Ukraine is an entry point.
uh Iran and Pakistan are actually
rimland nations and they're not quite
heartland entry points. Of course, if
you if the US manages to conquer Iran
and install a puppet regime in Iran,
then Russia isn't that far far away and
Russia is obviously a heartland nation.
Um now Russia in Iran, Russia is
handling Ukraine. I'm not sure how
Russia is handling Ukraine. Russia is
currently in a proxy war with NATO in
Ukraine. It's not handling Ukraine and
India is not handling Pakistan. India is
is being saddled with this terrorist
nation which is a vasal of the west
which which is the vasal of the US.
Now you're asking why has RA abandoned
Iran? How has anybody abandoned Iran?
None of the R nations have any alliance
with Iran.
There is no alliance treaty between
either Russia or China or India either
jointly or collectively or or or
singularly with Iran. So how can anybody
make the claim that Iran has been
abandoned?
You abandon somebody only if you have a
treaty and then you don't abide by the
treaty of of uh mutual protection or
whatever. There is no such treaty.
Of course, Iran, you could say, is is
kind of an ally of of Russia and China,
and both nations have an interest in in
ensuring that Iran continues to exist.
We also have an interest in in ensuring
that Iran continues to exist. But when
the US, let's say, wants to destroy
Iran, for example, hypothetically, it
has attacked Iran, hasn't it? So, when
the US is involved directly, does it
make sense for India to get involved in
the matter?
Just realistically and practically India
should stay out of it. Now China if you
look at the map it is so far away from
Iran. What can China do? Russia is the
closest to Iran. So if push push comes
to shove maybe Russia may consider
possibly uh getting involved in some
way. But it is completely uh not correct
to say that RI has abandoned Iran. Iran
was never an ally. You abandon somebody
somebody only if you have an alliance
treaty and then you don't ab ab ab ab ab
ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab
ab ab abideide by it and obviously the
main driving factor is how powerful the
US is. People don't realize how powerful
the US is. I have been saying this from
the rooftops
the US has never been as powerful as it
is today but people don't seem to
realize this. Maybe you you're watching
your favorite YouTuber or favorite news
readader on on your favorite news
channel who are saying the US is
declining.
What utter nonsense. The US has never
been as powerful as it is today.
Right. Okay.
Now, a history question by anonymous
scientist. Which civilization or culture
succeeded the Indus Valley culture
civilization?
Marxist historians say there's a gap or
blah blah blah blah blah. And this blah
blah blah explains Arian picnic tourism
theory. Marxist historians say there's a
gap or cultural discontinuity.
And this gap or discontinuity explains
the Arian picnic tourism theory.
Now show me the gap. I don't care what
somebody said. Show me the gap.
There is clear cultural continuity
archaeological record of clear cultural
continuity that goes back 9 and a half
10,000 years.
And the IVC, the Indus Valley
civilization so-called was not some
separate civilization that that
disappeared.
It was one period of our history
and it never went away. It never went
away. It still exists. We are the
continuation.
the cultural and civilizational elements
that you see in the archaeological
record during the so-called indust
valley times Harapan times whatever
Sarasindu times the same cultural
religious ar and and civilizational
traits are even seen today
so it's completely wrong it's completely
false what these Marxist historians have
been claiming okay
Um
right okay let's uh
uh Yashwan says is the US deep state
allowing Trump family business deal so
as to have skin in Balojasthan and later
later leverage this as justification for
military operations when the rebels
fight against this
so Trump clearly has
business deals in Pakistan we all know
that I've I've shown that very clearly
in in great detail haven't I can look
you could fact check everything I've
said. You can fact check as much as you
want. Nobody will be able to deny it
what I have revealed. Right? Um so the
Trump family has this extensive business
dealings in Pakistan. Why
is it being allowed? Clearly there are
conflicts of interest. The US president
is not supposed to be directly involved
in such matters. So why is it being
allowed is the question you are asking.
If a deep state exists, they would like
definitely Trump to have skin in the
game in Balojasthan.
Um see when it comes to the US Pakistan,
it's not about Balojasthan. It's about
Pakistan. Trump doesn't give two two
hoots about Baluchistan. Trump doesn't
care. He's there to exploit the land,
oil, gas, rare earths, and also crypto
stuff because he's making a pivot
towards cryptocurrency from being a real
estate guy. Um, so it's about
the the nation of Pakistan is super
important to the US because it it serves
so many purposes. It it it's a it's a
gateway to Afghanistan. It's a gateway
to Central Asia. It can be used to keep
an eye on Persia on it. It can be used
to continuously bleed India via various
terroristic activities. It can even be
used to infiltrate China for some in
some ways and be a conduit towards
China. So Pakistan is very important and
why not have a US president who
personally invested in Pakistan? Well,
then he'll be it'll be sufficient
motivation for him to to promote the
interests of Pakistan like for example
preventing India from destroying
Pakistan completely in May. So that's
the reason why.
Okay. Um
okay Dick Dick Chickmaster says longtime
viewer. Well thank you so much. Thank
you so much for being a longtime viewer.
I appreciate that. So the question is
Iran having nukes would be be bad for us
Indians too. Kam compared the life of
Muslims in India to Gaza. Yet Iran is
geopolitically important for us. How to
view? So I have said this in the past.
I'm saying it. I'll say it today also. I
would not want Iran to have nukes. We
already have one nuclear headache in the
region which is Pakistan. We don't want
another one because you know like I've
the analogy I give is that of a cat
right let's say you have a cat nice
little house cat a standard standard
issue cat big this big right and you
know how cats behave they're very nice
and cute and they were sharp claws and
teeth but they're really nice they meow
now imagine something happens to your
cat and your cat becomes four times as
big so from this size the cat goes to
that size so the cat becomes the size of
a cheetah or a leopard do you think your
cat will behave the same way as as when
he was that that size. No, the behavior
will change according to the size. Your
same cat with the same personality the
moment he goes from this size to the
cheetah size or leopard size will
acquire a new personality commensurate
with his new status and new size and new
strength. Right? Similarly, a nation
which doesn't have nuclear weapons, if
you give nuclear weapons to it, it will
I promise you act very differently. And
we don't want that. But listen, we need
Iran to continue to exist in the same
way it is right now in the same shape
and form. Otherwise, the entire region
falls to the US and every nation becomes
anti-India.
So yeah,
that's how we that's how we view it.
Rams is breaking a piece of news over
here. Iran has fired six missiles to
bases in Qatar.
Well, those are not Qatari bases, I
imagine. I haven't seen the news thus
far. I'll see it after this is over this
live stream. But this must be at US I I
imagine this would be at US bases in
Qatar which would be Wow.
Escalation escalation.
Okay.
Uh okay. Kamill Kamill says
Kamill Kamal I don't know Kamill says
China is going to sell 40 J35 fighter
planes to Pakistan. Is our 4.5
generation Rafal fighter plane good
enough to go head-to-head with them.
Shouldn't we try to pump as much money,
efforts, and all resources to get our
AMCA in two years?
Well, we are faced with the situation
now. I am not sure how good or not so
good the J35 may or may not be. We know
it's it's a fifth generation fighter
plane and we have to assume it's as at
least as good as F-35.
The F-35 I've always said is a flying
trash can but it's still a fifth
generation fighter plane
and uh yeah so if the Chinese sell 40
J35s to Pakistan well I think the
Chinese need to do some thinking now
right especially in in the light of the
Iran situation if Iran potentially falls
if it I think there's a small chance of
that happening but if it does then China
loses access to a tremendous supply
ongoing supply of cheap energy
and also an allied nation at least quasa
allied nation.
Do they still want to be enemies with
India all the time? Does it make sense
for for China to continue to be our
enemy and support a nation that is a US
vasal?
I mean if China sells the AJ35 to
Pakistan,
the first thing that will happen is is
that US technicians will take it apart
will take one of those or two of those
and take it apart and get all the
Chinese secrets. Do the Chinese want
that?
So yeah, but let's let's assume they do
for example for what for for whatever
reason. Then the question is is the
Rafal good enough to go headto-head with
that? Well, I would assume that if the
J35 is a decent fifth generation fighter
plane, then the Rafal is not good
enough.
Okay, then the question you ask is
should we not try and pump in money,
efforts, all that to get the AMCA in two
years? Impossible.
Fighter plane development timelines are
very long. It's going to take at least 5
years. I I hear that there's going to be
a prototype in the next year or two AMCA
and maybe it'll start flying in the next
2 3 years perhaps. So we can try and
make that happen as fast as possible and
maybe shorten the the iteration cycle or
whatever but but we have to assume that
it takes the time it takes to have a
production worthy fighter plane. So what
generally happens is that you have a set
of blueprints and you base the
blueprints on the lessons you've learned
from the previous aircraft you you
designed and flew which is the so we've
learned a lot from the project. We take
all those learnings we make a blueprint
for the AMCA then you cut the metal and
do all that stuff and you create a
prototype and you test it out. That's
your prototype number one. Then
obviously it will have some flaws and
deficiencies. Though you make a second
prototype and this time you put engines
and you make it fly and hopefully it
works fine. But once again you see the
flight characteristics and whatnot. Then
once again you modify it and improve it
and have a third prototype and around
that time third fourth fourth prototype
it's reasonably flying worthy. So that's
your first production production version
of the aircraft. This whole process will
take at least 5 seven years. That's how
it goes. Uh but I'm sure it's possible
to shorten the time period instead of 7
to 10 years. Make make it five years by
which we have uh
uh product production versions and
induction into the uh into the air
force. So listen, it's it's no one's
fault but ours that we are in the
situation. We've been delaying our
things so long so long so long. So yeah,
we need to now get going on a war
footing. And the good thing is that the
go government of India acts only when
there are massive threats and pressure
from outside. So I think here we are now
it's going to act. So hopefully things
uh change.
Yash says India might find a Guyana size
sized India might find Guyana sized oil
fields in the underman sea worth more
than 20 trillion USD.
If that happens, what do you think will
be? What do you think? Will we be
self-reliable, self-reliant in energy
requirements? If that happens, we will
be 100% self-reliant in energy. We'll
also be a net exporter of energy. The
question is, have we found this? I think
Mr. Harp Singh Puri made a statement
recently that we may be on the verge of
discovering something like that. Well,
being on the verge of something is
great.
But it's not actually discovering it
yet. So let's wait and watch. I think if
you look at the Indian Ocean region, the
eastern coast, the western coast of
India, I think there'll be tremendous
quantities of oil and gas there. We
simply have not bothered to look. We
have simply been lazy. It's only this
government finally which is waking up
now and looking into these things. I
think we we may find way more what than
what the Arabs have. If we just look
properly not just offshore but also
onshore.
So let's say sometime in the next few
months we make the announcement that we
have discovered ginormous oil field
worth more than 20 20 trillion USD. It
will be enough to take care of our
energy self-sufficiency and also become
make India net exporter of energy. It
will also mean that we will have to
significantly
militarize the under demand region, put
up air bases, naval bases there to
safeguard our assets and so on. So yeah,
um
Flick edits says, "How might a prolonged
Iran Israel confrontation affect global
oil markets and trade corridors,
especially in light of alternative
routes like the India Middle East Europe
Economic Corridor?" Okay.
So, here's let's let's go to the map and
put that on the screen.
So, let's say that Iran is being hit
very badly. So, what Iran could do in
retaliation is close down this choke
point. Okay, this is a very very narrow
choke point. It's called the straight of
Hormuz. Just 100 kilometers. And Iran
has significant naval facilities here.
They can lay mines in the ocean which
could destroy ships which pass through
the region and so on and this could
completely block the state of Hormos.
And why is it very important? Because a
significant quantity of the world's
energy flows through the state of
Hormos. Uh it comes from the oil fields
in Kuwait, in Saudi Arabia, in Iran, in
Iraq, etc. And it all flows, it all has
to flow through the state of Hormos
through oil tankers. Okay? So if Iran
shuts that down then oil prices will
shoot up and you will have a global
crisis and this could create a global
recession.
Okay.
So that is something that could disrupt
the the affect the over the global oil
markets and it's yeah then then
obviously the prices of everything go
up. Now the India Middle East Europe
economic corridor is not an alternative
route.
How is it an alternative route? That's a
totally different thing. It's not a
corridor through which oil passes. It's
not even been constructed. It's still on
paper. Uh so the IMAC is just on paper.
It's supposed to connect let's say
western India for example, Mumbai uh
through Saudi Arabia
all the way into through Jordan and into
Israel and from there into through
Cyprus and then into Greece bypassing
Turkey. That's the plan. It's on paper.
Nothing has happened thus far.
So yeah. So if if the straight of hormos
is choked up by Iran and if the Houthis
in Yemen etc they also become active
then even the the Red Sea the straight
of Bab al- Mandib over here even that
could be closed down which would mean
that much of the shipping and all that
will have to pass through pass by the
Cape of Good Hope which will
significantly increase costs beyond what
we already have. So these are the
scenarios that could you know play out.
Okay. Bhavy says is is this a live
stream? Okay. Somebody please help him
out and explain if it is a live stream
or not. Um
Sam the gamer says why do you think our
navy do no do you think our navy navy is
significantly behind in submarines just
like the lack of squadrons in the air
force? Our Navy is significantly behind
in in submarines. Okay, let's let's do a
comparison. See, Joseph Stalin said that
quantity has a quality of its own.
Forget about quality. First work on
quantity. How many North submarines
uh how many submarine submarines
does North Korea have? See this
64 to 86 submarines. Okay, North Korea.
Now, let's say Japan.
Japan has 22.
Okay, how many does the US have? The US
only has nuclear submarines. The US has
70 submarines. How about France?
Nine submarines. It's a small nation.
What about the UK?
UK also nine. But what about China?
Uh 61 submarines.
Okay, let's also see Pakistan
eight subordinates. So 61 for China,
eight for Pakistan, about 80 for North
Korea. Let's see India, we have like 15
or 16, I would say 17
conventional three nuclear power. I
think for a nation of our enormous
coastline having 20 submarines is a
joke.
We should have way more. We should have
close to 100 submarines
or at least 50 submarines, right? North
Korea has almost 80 submarines. So, we
are significantly behind in submarines
and we have been we have been napping
essentially.
Okay. Um
let us see. Okay. Arian Musk says a lot
of nations want to beat down US
hedgemony even if they are US allies and
today it's evident that the US is not
united anymore there's a lot of major
differences are there what are their
views
okay what's the question how many
questions do we have here a lot of
nations want to beat down the US and
Germany even if they are US allies no
they're not allies they're vasals but
they're called allies in a in polite
language okay for example France France
is a member of the EU. France is a
member of NATO because of which it has
lost sovereignty. It doesn't have full
sovereignty over over its own well its
own resources, its assets. It's not a
fully sovereign nation. France would
love nothing more than to be 100% fully
sovereign once again. So yeah, that will
only happen if US hedgemony declines.
The the UK is a complete vasal. They
don't even have any aspiration of of
being free.
Italy is another and so on, Japan, South
Korea and so on, Australia, New Zealand.
All Australia would love nothing more
than to have even more US sovereignty
and hedgemony, but whatever. So there's
lot of nations that would love to be
free again,
right? So that's true. No question. And
the other question is the US is not so
united anymore. Lots of differences,
major differences. That's domestic
differences. The US society is in major
decline, qualitative decline. US hard
power has never been as high as it is
now. The US has never been more powerful
than it is today. But you can see
visible decline in the quality of the
society. Moral decay, societal decay,
all of that. Lots of differences in US
society. People can't agree with each
other. Even if they disagree in the
past, they could be they could be social
with each other. They could be polite
and civilized. Today, they can't. And so
on all kinds of issues in in US society.
So overall the quality of US society is
declining. There is moral decay and and
so much more in the US society. All the
institutions seem to be decaying. The
education system is is is terrible now
compared to what it was in the 1950s
and60s and so on and so forth. So
overall yeah that's that's the way it
is.
Okay. Um
uh Anand Chanduk says, "How to make a
submarine at home?" Any easy technology
to do that?
You can also ask me how to make a
nuclear weapon at home, right?
How do you make a submarine at home?
Look, that's not really very classified
technology. The first submarines were
made more than 100 years ago. During the
first world war, the Germans had these
unus boots, u boots, lots of them, and
so on. So it's not that difficult how to
make I'm sure you can see you can find
blueprints and whatnot online of of
older submarines. It's not very
classified technology. It's just that
it's very difficult for one person to do
it. Even if you build one at your home,
do you have a river or a sea in your
home?
Yeah. So
um
Ujiha says Iran strikes the Qatar air
bases. Somebody tell us sir please. Well
you have told the sir yourself my
friend. Okay so I've been hearing this.
Iran is has struck at Qatar bases. Let
me see news.
Shall I see news? Uh let's let's see it
together shall we? I just opened Google
news.
Um um um so Iran Israel okay that is an
old news that is old news Iran blah blah
blah.
What happened what we know so far five
let's look at Qatar
let's look at Qatar what's going on
UK US Qatar shuts airspace Iran
retaliates fires missiles at US bases in
Qatar.
Okay. Okay. Several explosions heard
over DHA. My god, it's going to destroy
people's businesses.
Okay.
Iran retaliates.
Let's take a look at this one. Let's
quickly uh read the news in real time by
Al Monitor. Iran retaliates, fires
missiles at US bases in Qatar and in
Iraq.
Okay, this is over Natana. That's
different. Um, Iran has launched at
least 10 missiles towards US bases in
Qatar, one towards Iraq. Um, Qatar hosts
the largest US military presence in the
Middle East with more than 8,000 troops
stationed in Alud air base outside DHA.
Explosions were heard over KQataril DHA.
According to AFP, others
uh according to Iran, Iran's missile
operation against US bases in Qatar and
Iraq has begun under the name blessings
of victory
and so on. Okay. So this is all breaking
news. This is happening as we speak. So
as we can see there is escalation.
Well, what do you expect?
Um yeah. So okay, I'll keep an eye on
this for sure. I will. Har Chan Haran
Google says does mass producing multiple
does mass producing multi-roll fighters
compensate for not having different
kinds of aircraft bombers and
surveillance aircraft? To some extent it
can. So let's say you don't have heavy
strategic bombers but you have uh
multi-roll fighters. So you can use
multiroll fighters for bombing missions
for sure can't you? Right? You can. So
let's say you produce a thousand
multi-roll fighters. Well that can
certainly offset the requirement for for
dedicated bombing aircraft. So yeah it
it can work. Quantity has a quality of
its own.
Um,
okay.
Some of the questions before we end.
Today is going to be a 60-minute live
stream. We're going to do more. So,
yeah.
RDRA says, Rudra asked a very good
question. Look at this. How many points
will India and China gain in Chava index
if they become energy independent?
Uh, that is something I have to
calculate. But India's energy security
well it's it's a major component of uh
of your hard power and that's the the
fact that India is not energy
energetically self-sufficient it's a
significant drawback for India and it
decreases India's score so right now
India's score is about 4.91 it may rise
up to five 5.5 maybe six maybe even
beyond that I'll have to see
good question it will certainly make a
significant difference for sure
Okay,
Mahesa says, "What is I I saw this
question one time before also. Um, what
is so special about the Great Wall of
China?" Um, the Great Wall of China.
Well, I'll tell you what's special about
it. Okay, let's let's take a look at the
map. It actually the special thing is
that it tells you what China really is
and where China's limits are, boundaries
are great wall
of China. What am I writing? Wina,
China. Great. Greta,
Great Wall of China. It's giving me one
single location. Shang Joo.
Okay, let's look. Let's look somewhere
else. Let's let's uh let's look here.
Give me a second.
Um here.
Great wall of Shin
Lashin. Okay, let's look at images.
Okay, let's look at map.
So now this tells us look where was the
great great wall of China? It was here.
So that tells you where the limits of
China are. Okay. Um
these these are the original boundaries
of China. China actually has has taken
over a lot of territory that doesn't
belong to it. So that's one of the most
important indications from the Great
Wall of China. And they regarded
everybody beyond the Great Wall as
barbarians.
So it's an indicator of what China's
historical boundaries were, what its
historical uh extent
was and other stuff whatever else could
be special or not I don't know. Okay.
Uh geopolitical says Ramayan has many
versions. The Thai king is still called
the king Rama the 10th or 11th or
whatever. Albania Prime Minister Adi
Rama but why the Mahabharat has not
virgin like Ramayan and not popular in
other countries like Ramayana. Uh
Albania has nothing to do with India by
the way as far as I understand. I may be
wrong but as far as I know there's no
connection. Why doesn't the Mahabharat
have so many other versions? I'm not
sure I can answer the question. I'm not
sure. I'm not aware.
Um
the Mahabharat was more like a civil
war, wasn't it, for us?
Um
because it is us fighting us. The Raman
was a different story. It was um yeah
listen I don't I don't have the answer
right now. I'm not sure. I have not
looked into this question
but maybe the Raman was way more popular
than than the Mahabharat in the past
possibly. I'm not sure.
Um
okay let's take a few more questions
before we end.
Um, Priyanu says the characteristics of
a nation or an empire, these
characteristics depend on the founder.
Who should we call the founder of modern
independent India?
I have no idea who's the founder. I'll
tell you who's the founder. The British
are the founders of modern independent
India. It was a transfer of power from
the British to their handpicked minions.
And the characteristics of modern day
India are pretty mediocre, aren't they?
Despite all the potential, despite
having the greatest potential of any
civilization or any nation in the world,
we are currently a nation of great
mediocrity.
So those are the characteristics of our
so-called founders.
But I'll tell you what, we are a
civilization state. We were not founded
in 1947.
It was just a transition period.
So I don't know who or so-called we
don't have any founding fathers as such
or and if somebody has to be given the
title of founding fathers I would give
it to the great historic historical
Greeks Lord Ram Lord emperor Barat Lord
Ram Lord Krishna and so many of our
great emperors in the past and even they
you can't say founded India I mean did
Chandra Gupta Moria and uh Vishnu Gupta
Tanaki found India bat no they did not
they simply continued something that was
much older than them. Kaneshka, no. The
Gupta emperors, no. The Chola, the great
Cholas, no. They all continued something
that already existed.
So I think the founder of I don't modern
independ independ independent India is a
passing phase. We should remain
independent but we should become great
again. This is a period of mediocrity
and I have no I can't think of a single
person who deserves the title of the
founder of India. The only real founder
of India I would say is is King Bat
back in the day.
Okay. Amisha says some people are saying
that that Israel is now the US
the US's master after the US dropped
bombs in Iran. Is this true in the
current situation? It looks incliningly
more likely that it's the case, doesn't
it?
Looks increasingly like likely
increasingly more likely that that's the
case. the US will do whatever it takes
to to to support Israel and to advance
Israeli interests. Trump used to to
shout from the rooftops that I'm the
only US president in I don't know how
many decades who did not start a new war
and I did not drop bombs on anyone and
so on used to say well look what he's
doing right now.
Yeah.
The question is why? Well, clearly he
there is some influence in the US that
Israel has. Not some influence, very
significant influence if you can get the
US president to drop bombs for you on
your adversaries.
And why is it the case? Um,
I'm not going there.
Okay.
All right. Um,
let's see. Um
okay Yashprit says is a military
alliance just a formal agreement or can
the same benefits be enjoyed without
alliance also should India build an
alliance as the US there's a risk of US
sanctions
a military alliance is indeed a formal
agreement it's a treaty and alliance is
generally based on a treaty that two
nations sign typically it's a mutual
defense treaty that if I am attacked you
will come to my aid. If you are
attacked, I'll come to your aid. And you
formalize that by signing a treaty. That
makes it a formal alliance, a military
alliance. Then there are other kinds of
alliances like economic alliances and so
on, but we're talking about military
alliances here. So, it's usually a
mutual self-defense agreement.
Can the same benefits be enjoyed without
alliances? I suppose you can you can
have an informal alliance, I suppose,
without actually signing a treaty. That
can happen. Um
for example, India and Bhutan don't have
s such a treaty but I'm sure that if
Bhutan faces any trouble, India will
come to its defense so on uh should
India build an alliance is there a risk
of US sanctions. The whole world faces
the risk of US sanctions. So I suppose
see you can't you can't counter economic
sanctions through a military alliance
especially not against the US. So it
doesn't work that way.
Namin Kumar asks is Pakistan really a
nuclear nation or is is it just carrying
US nuclear weapons with only US
officials having operational power? I
think it is very likely that Pakistan
is is hosting US nuclear warheads and it
is very likely that it is US officials
who have the the actual operational
power over those warheads. I am I I have
come to the conclusion that Pakistan has
never been capable of building a nuclear
bomb on its own. it simply did not
doesn't have the mental bandwidth
bandwidth to to do to do that despite
being the same DNA as us because other
things apart from DNA also matter. So I
don't think Pakistan ever developed
nuclear weapons. I think it's US nuclear
weapons aimed at India hosted in
Pakistan soil which tells you what kind
of relationship the the US has and what
kind of attitude the US has towards
India.
Okay Shaspat sir thank you so much for
becoming a member. I never ask anybody
for being becoming a member but people
still do. So thank you so much. I
genuinely really very humbly appreciate
the support.
Um
okay. A says operation Sundur 2. Israel
will go after Pakistan. Israel is not
ever going after Pakistan.
Pakistan is a US US ally and by that
it's also a de facto Israeli ally.
Okay. So, Israel is not going after
Pakistan. Some Israeli politicians may
have said some things in the past.
Please, my viewers, if you learn only
one thing from watching me, please learn
that words and actions are separate
things. Words
are can be meaningless. Words can be
empty. Words are cheap. Words cost
nothing.
Anybody can say anything and tomorrow
says do something else. Israel is not
going after Pakistan. McLevin says,
"What will be the impact on the Armenia
war now as it's proven our system is
better than Israel? Both is Israel and
Turkey are against Armenia and now we
are shipping a second batch of Akash
missiles." Well, the impact is that it
should hopefully bolster Armenia's
defenses against Azarbaijan. Isn't it
very interesting? Really interesting.
Isn't it noteworthy that India supports
Armenia
and Israel supports Armenia's enemy
Azarbaijan?
So Israel and Turkey support Armenia's
enemy and India supports Armenia. So we
are on opposite sides with Israel. We
are Israel is our adversary here and
Israel is standing with Turkey in this.
So the impact is that if we supply more
weapons to Armenia, the chances of of of
u
of defending themselves increase that's
the impact.
Amisha says if the universe is 20
billion years old and what hap what
existed be before that very mysterious
the universe to the best that to to the
best of our understanding the universe
is about 13.8
billion years old. What existed before
that? Well, that that's something we
can't really answer because we don't
have data of what came what is what may
potentially be beyond outside the
universe. Um there are multiple theories
there there's there's a theory of a
cyclical universe um um in which
universe um
conformal cyclical cosmology Roger
Penrose and his theory and there is the
big bounce model that the universe will
expand then it'll contract again and
then bounce off again that sort of
thing. So there are multiple theories
out there but we don't have any evidence
that goes in favor of any of these
theories. We can't say for sure. So this
is all in the realm of theory right now.
There is no evidence but we have
multiple theories.
Okay.
Um
maybe we can take maybe one or two
questions more.
Uh Mobile Menace says can I get a shout
out from my channel Kishnamri? I make
content on cool cool weapons and
creatures in our script scriptures.
Thank you. Well, here we have it.
Krishna Mria shout out.
Um,
Anchul says, "How did the solar system
form? Were the planets always in the
same positions or their positions
shifted from time to time? Why are
Uranus and Neptune at the age edge of
the solar system?" The solar system, how
did it form? It formed about 4.5 billion
years ago. The universe is about 13.8
billion years old. Okay? And the solar
system formed about 4.5 billion years
ago. It formed from a gigantic cloud of
dust and gas.
Where did that cloud come from? That
cloud came from the death of a previous
star.
So the sun is a reincarnated star.
It's in its possibly third reincarnation
possibly.
So at least second reincarnation.
And so from that big cloud of gas and
dust, you had the formation of a
protostellar disc. If you want to know
know what that looks like, let me show
you. It's a flat disc, swirling disc of
gas. Pro
protostellar
not protostellar you can also call it a
pro protolanetary disc. So this is what
it looks like right this is an actual
one photographed and this is what it
looks like theoretically and eventually
because of the pressure and so on the
star ignites at the center and uh and
then clumps form around it which give
rise to the planets and that's how it
goes. So that is how uh the solar system
was formed. The planets were not
necessarily in the same positions. Okay.
The the positions shift over time and
they will shift they will shift on over
time in the future also. Some planets
may actually get ejected out of out of
the solar system because of the complex
dynamics gravitational dynamics and
Uranus and Neptune are the edge of the
solar system because of the way the
whole solar system evolved. The earth in
the past about 4 something billion years
ago suffered a massive impact impact by
another ancient planet which is now part
of the earth and the consequence of the
impact most likely was that there was a
big amount of material that was ejected
which formed a ring initially around the
earth and that coalesed later into a
glob into a blob which became the moon
and so on.
A says Iran is part of bricks. Does that
not count as an alliance? BRICS is an
economic coalition. It's not an alliance
and there is no military dimension to
bricks. So that's your answer.
Okay, I think we're going to end this
session over here. Okay, let's take one
last question by our good old friend
Shri Ramachandra. Not old but good
friend. So the question is how does any
country decide to buy which weapons? How
does a country decide which weapons to
buy? They have defense experts. But do
TV, news, propaganda or nar narratives
effect affect the kind of weapons you
buy. See, ideally you probably produce
your own weapons. But let's say you
don't have the technology and you're not
good at that and all. Then you have to
buy weapons. So how do you decide what
to buy? You decide what weapons to buy
based on your threat assessment.
It depends on whether you're a maritime
nation, you're a landlocked nation or a
nation with a coast. And then it depends
on what kind of neighbors do you have.
They are friendly. Are they friendly?
Are they adversarial? Are they
genocidal?
All those factors and your geography in
all these different parameters they cons
they they create they create your
overall big picture threat perception
and based on the threat perception your
military tells you that these are the
weapons we need to successfully defend
the country and and and
u and take care of the national
interest. So based on that you decide
that okay I need to have an air force
that is that has these capabilities.
Maybe I just need uh interceptors or
maybe I need longrange bombers or maybe
I need whatever. So it depends on that.
How many helicopters I need? In case I
do if I if I need a navy, how many ships
do I need to defend my my my coastline?
How many submarines do I need? Do I have
expansionist ambitions? In that case, do
I may need a different kind of navy and
air force and infantry and number of
tanks and whatnot. So that's how we do
it. And um so nations have military
personnel, defense experts. Uh does TV
news propaganda narrative affect it?
Only if it's a corrupt and and and not
very robust nation. Otherwise TV news
propaganda and all that. If it is
antinational, if it is counterproductive
to the nation, it should be nipped at
the bud. But if it's a democratic
nation, everything affects it. All
right.
All right.
Okay.
So I think with that we're going to end
today's live stream. So thank you so
much everybody for
Okay, now what is this? One second. Uh
yeah. Okay. So we're going to end this
live stream over here. Thank you so much
everybody for all your questions and I
will see you in the next live stream and
in the next episode of Jee Strategy
which will come before the next live
stream. Thank you so much. Keep asking
questions. I enjoyed this one today.
Good questions. So take care. Keep
asking questions. Keep learning. Keep
raising your standards and I'll see you
next time. Thank you so much.